Register of the Frank B. and Josephine Whitney Duveneck collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Frank B. and Josephine Whitney Duveneck collection,
1936-1974
88031
Duveneck, Frank B., collector
8 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Pamphlets, leaflets, reports, bulletins, newsletters, statements, Congressional hearings, serial issues, and clippings, relating to the internment of Japanese Americans in the United States during World War II; social problems in the United States, especially in California, and especially with reference to migrant farm workers, sharecroppers, blacks, and American Indians; race relations in the United States; and progressive education programs. Collected by Frank B. and Josephine Whitney Duveneck. Includes a few letters written to the Duvenecks.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1886 Birth of Frank B. Duveneck, Florence, Italy
1891 Birth of Josephine Whitney, Brookline, Massachusetts
1913 Marriage of Frank B. Duveneck and Josephine Whitney
1920s Josephine Whitney Duveneck serves on the Palo Alto City Council
1924 Purchase of Hidden Villa Ranch, Los Altos, California, which later becomes a summer camp for children and a youth hostel
1942-1945 Both Duvenecks are active on behalf of evacuated Japanese Americans
1978 Publication of Life on Two Levels, the autobiography of Josephine Whitney Duveneck Death of Josephine Whitney Duveneck
1985 Death of Frank B. Duveneck
Scope and Content Note
Received in the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988, with an increment in 1998, the Duveneck collection reflects the lifelong social activism of Frank B. Duveneck and Josephine Whitney Duveneck. The causes taken up by the Duvenecks included the plight of migrant farm workers in the United States; the promotion of racial equality in American society; concern for the status of American Indians; and the defense of Japanese Americans who were relocated during World War II. In addition, the Duvenecks devoted time to running an integrated summer camp for children and were active in the Society of Friends (Quakers).
The collection includes material relating to these issues. Of particular interest are those documents relating to the relocation of Japanese Americans, including government publications, letters of protest, and Frank B. Duveneck's personal correspondence with evacuees (see SUBJECT FILE). The collection also includes numerous publications and photographs documenting the living conditions of migrant agricultural workers and Indians in the United States (see SUBJECT FILE and PHOTOGRAPHS), as well as material pertaining to Josephine Whitney Duveneck's activities as a member of various civil rights organizations in California (see SUBJECT FILE).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
World War, 1939-1945--United States.; Migrant agricultural laborers.; Share-cropping.; Land tenure--United States.; Education--United States.; African Americans; Indians of North America.; United States.; California.; World War, 1939-1945.; Education.; United States--Race relations.; United States--Social conditions.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; Duveneck, Josephine Whitney, 1891-
Container List
- Biographical File, 1955-1966. (Box 1)
  Bibliography, clippings, and correspondence, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Bibliography, n.d. (Folder 1: 1)
    Holograph
  - Clippings, 1960-1966 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Correspondence relating to the award of an honorable mention to Josephine W. Duveneck by the Lane Bryant Annual Award committee, 1955 (Folder 1: 3)
- Correspondence, 1941-1974. (Box 1)
  Letters of Frank B. and Josephine Whitney Duveneck, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Elkus, Marjorie, 1948 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1941 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Kingman, Ruth, 1974 (Folder 1: 6)
- Speeches and Writings, 1942-1978. (Box 1)
  Autobiography, letters to the editor, speeches, and writings, arranged by the names of the Duvenecks and therein chronologically by title
  - Duveneck, Frank B.
    - Letter to the editor, New York Times, 1942 April 12. (Folder 1: 7)
      Printed copy
    - Letter to the editor, The Nation, 1942 May 9. (Folder 1: 8)
  - Duveneck, Josephine Whitney
    - Speech on Quakerism, n.d. (Folder 1: 9)
      Typescript
    - Writing on progressive education, n.d. (Folder 1: 10)
      Holograph (incomplete)
    - Writing on relocation of Japanese Americans, n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
    - Speech to California Federation for Civic Unity, 1948(?). (Folder 1: 12)
    - Poem, 1957. (Folder 1: 13)
    - Life on Two Levels, autobiography, 1978. (Folder 1: 14)
      Typescript (incomplete)
- Subject File, 1936-1974. (Box 1-8)
  Bulletins, clippings, Congressional hearings transcripts, correspondence, leaflets, maps, minutes, newsletters, pamphlets, reports, and serial issues, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - American Friends Service Committee (Folder 1: 15-16)
  - Civil rights--United States. (Folder 1: 17-20)
    Includes material relating to the California Federation for Civic Unity and the Council for Civic Unity of San Francisco
  - Civil rights--United States. (Contd.) (Folder 2: 1-3)
  - Education--United States (Folder 2: 4-5)
  - Housing--United States (Folder 2: 6)
  - Indians of North America
    - Correspondence, 1937-1958. (Folder 2: 7)
      Letters neither to nor from Frank B. and Josephine Whitney Duveneck, and relating to the American Association on Indian Affairs and the California Indian Defense Committee. Correspondents include E. Raymond Armsby, Charles de Y. Elkus, and Oliver La Farge
    - Maps (Folder 2: 8)
    - Printed matter (Folder 2: 9)
    - Printed matter (Contd.) (Folder 3: 1-7)
    - Printed matter (Contd.) (Folder 4: 1-5)
    - Printed matter (Contd.) (Folder 5: 1-2)
  - Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945
    - Correspondence, largely involving Frank B. Duveneck's efforts on behalf of evacuees, 1942-1944
      - General (Folder 5: 3)
      - Evacuees
        - General (Folder 5: 4)
        - Takahashi, Shozaburo (Folder 5: 5)
    - Printed matter (Folder 5: 6-8)
  - McCarthy, Joseph (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Migrant agricultural workers--United States (Folder 6: 2-7)
  - Migrant agricultural workers--United States (Contd.) (Folder 7: 1-2)
  - Private Camp Integration Study Group
    - Correspondence, largely involving Josephine Whitney Duveneck, 1964-1970 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Minutes and reports (Folder 7: 4-5)
  - Southern Tenant Farmers Union (Folder 7: 6)
  - United Farm Workers of America (UFWA) (Folder 7: 7)
  - United States. Farm Security Administration., See also Migrant agricultural workers--United States (Box-folder 8: 1-4)
- Photographs, 1954. (Box 8)
  38 prints depicting the members of a convention of the California Federation for Civic Unity, American Indian arts and crafts, migrant agricultural workers and their children, and a neighborhood improvement program
  - 1 print depicting the members (including Josephine Whitney Duveneck?) of a convention of the California Federation for Civic Unity, Asilomar, California, 1954 (Folder 8: 5)
  - 3 prints depicting American Indian arts and crafts, n.d. (Folder 8: 6)
  - 3 prints depicting living facilities in a camp for migrant agricultural workers, n.d. (Folder 8: 7)
  - 16 prints depicting an educational program for the children of migrant agricultural workers, n.d. (Folder 8: 8)
  - 10 prints depicting migrant agricultural workers and their children, n.d. (Folder 8: 9)
  - 5 prints and 2 sheets of contact prints depicting a neighborhood improvement program in Menlo Park, California, n.d. (Folder 8: 10)